<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fisher-man A sermon preached at a synode held at Southwell in Nottinghamshire. Shewing 1. The necessitie of calling and gifts enabling in a minister. 2. The danger intruders are in. 3. Whose fault it is that such are in the Church. 4. A good life requisite in all that professe Christianitie, but especially in ministers. 5. Wisedome and learning absolutely necessary in preachers. 6. Vnlearned &amp; frothy preaching doth much hurt. 7. Gods worke goeth best forward when his workmen agree well amongst themselues. 8. Contempt of Gods ministers shall not be vnpunished. With other points of moment. By Ierom Phillips Bachelour in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Phillips, Jerome, d. ca. 1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849940</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15114</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15114)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1149:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fisher-man A sermon preached at a synode held at Southwell in Nottinghamshire. Shewing 1. The necessitie of calling and gifts enabling in a minister. 2. The danger intruders are in. 3. Whose fault it is that such are in the Church. 4. A good life requisite in all that professe Christianitie, but especially in ministers. 5. Wisedome and learning absolutely necessary in preachers. 6. Vnlearned &amp; frothy preaching doth much hurt. 7. Gods worke goeth best forward when his workmen agree well amongst themselues. 8. Contempt of Gods ministers shall not be vnpunished. With other points of moment. By Ierom Phillips Bachelour in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Phillips, Jerome, d. ca. 1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for [i.e. by] W[illiam] I[ones] for Robert Bird, and are to be sold [by Thomas Pavier] in Ivie Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15114:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15114:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FISHER-MAN.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at a Synode held at Southwell in Nottinghamſhire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The neceſſitie of calling and gifts enabling in a Miniſter.</item>
                  <item>2. The danger intruders are in.</item>
                  <item>3. Whoſe fault it is that ſuch are in the Church.</item>
                  <item>4. A good life requiſite in all that profeſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, but eſpecially in Miniſters.</item>
                  <item>5. Wiſedome and learning abſolutely neceſſary in Preachers.</item>
                  <item>6. Vnlearned &amp; frothy preaching doth much hurt.</item>
                  <item>7. Gods worke goeth beſt forward when his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men agree well amongſt themſelues.</item>
                  <item>8. Contempt of Gods Miniſters ſhall not be vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. With other points of moment.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Ierom Phillips</hi> Bachelour in Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. I.</hi> for <hi>Robert Bird,</hi> and are to be ſold in Ivie Lane. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15114:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15114:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LORD, AND REVEREND FATHER in God, IOHN by diuine prouidence Biſhop of Lincolne, Lord Keeper of the great Seale of England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Preſent vnto your Lordſhips view this ſhort Diſcourſe of the trade of Fiſhing: Fiſhing for Men, the beſt trade that mortall men can ſpend their time in, though all come not to it with the beſt mindes: for ſome are fiſhers of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> trade, for this hope onely, that they may haply ſpeed, as once Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did,<note place="margin">Math. 17. vlt.</note> to caſt an angle into the ſea, and pull vp a fiſh with mony in the mouth of it. Such <hi>ſeeke their owne, and not the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But howſoeuer, they that come with good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the work, and perform it with good effect, cannot be free from the poiſon of Aſpes that lieth
<pb facs="tcp:15114:3"/> vnder the lips of ſome men. For if any exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie be ſound in any of our coate and calling, it is ſtrange to ſee how our aduerſaries inſult there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and exclaime againſt all of the Clergie; from the higheſt to the loweſt, as if thereby there were cauſe enough giuen to pull downe the whole fabrik of our Church, and for themſelues to take vp that crie of the curſed Edomites, <hi>Downe with it, downe with it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> 
               <hi>euen with the ground.</hi> VVe all haue our faults, and too many of vs too many: but what then? ſhall the innocent beare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with the nocent? Or ſhall the reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church be taxable for the crimes of ſome Church-men, which they cannot mend?</p>
            <p>Shall the Maiſter beare the blame, becauſe ſome of his Diſciples eate with vnwaſhen hands?</p>
            <p>I doubt not, but many a thouſand in the Land, Prelates, and other good Paſtors, that ſtand in peaceable conformitie with the Church, can as ill brooke ſcandalous life and vnſound doctrine in a Miniſter, as any of thoſe fiery ſpirited declamors.</p>
            <p>The Gouerners of the Church cannot be ſo cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect but through the craft and malice of man and Satan, ſome ſuch may craftily creep in; that ſhall diſhonor God and defile the prieſthood.<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since by the prouidence of God, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties
<pb facs="tcp:15114:3"/> moſt iudicious choice, you are called to ſo high a place of honour and weightie emploiment for the Church and Kingdome; it is the hope of good men, that the Church ſhall haue cauſe to reioyce much in your Honours aduancement: and that goodneſſe in you ſhall receiue no loſſe by the acceſſe of greatneſſe, but rather much gaine, <hi>In te factam eſſe hanc mutationem confido,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</note> 
               <hi>non de te, nec priori ſtatui tuo ſucceſſiſſe hanc promotionem, ſed acceſſiſſe.</hi> It is the confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them that conuerſed with your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip whileſt you liued in theſe parts, and in this confidence haue I bin bold to preſent your Honor with this little Treatiſe. I can ſay nothing for my ſelfe, why I ſhould be ſo bold, ſauing that the ſubiect requireth ſuch a Patron, and my ſelfe am yours in the ſeruice of the Church, hauing paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charge in your Lordſhips Dioceſſe. It was firſt made publike, I confeſſe, by deliuery in the Prouince and Dioceſse of that moſt reuerend Archbiſhop of Yorke, to whom I am much obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for many courteſies, according to his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed benignity towards all, euen of the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings in the cauſe of the Church: yet herein I thought to make ſomewhat an equall diuiſion betwixt his Grace and your Honour, ſince you
<pb facs="tcp:15114:4"/> both haue intereſt in me: that as it was preached by his Graces appointment; ſo now it may be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed vnder your Honours protection. Thus humbly crauing your Lordſhips acceptance, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to the God of grace and glorie. From Althorpe in the Iſle of Axholme.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips in all humble and dutifull obſeruance,</hi> Ierom Phillips.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15114:4"/>
            <head>THE FISHER-MAN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MARK. 1.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Follow me, and I will make you Fiſhers of Men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the ninth verſe of this Chapter, the Euangeliſt doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the Baptiſme, Faſting, Temptation and preaching of Chriſt. The next thing, is his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of others to the ſame worke of preaching. He calleth here two paire of brethren; <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> his brother.</p>
            <p>They were but men, yet he will make them workers together with God:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.</note> they were but ſimple fiſher-men, yet he will make them Fiſhers of men. <hi>Follow me, and I will make you Fiſhers of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider in the Text two parts:
<list>
                  <item>1. Calling; <hi>Follow me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Qualifying; <hi>I will make you Fiſhers of men.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Before I ſpeake of the parts, let me conſider the order and diſpoſition of the parts: Firſt, Calling;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15114:5"/> then, Qualifying. Firſt, <hi>Follow;</hi> then, <hi>be made fiſhers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This firſt calling of the Apoſtles, is not to the worke of Apoſtleſhip, but rather to the ſchoole of Diſcipleſhip. It is not
<hi>Follow me,</hi> and ſtraightwayes be fiſhers; but, <hi>Follow, and I will make you Fiſhers.</hi> Neither did theſe fiſhers vpon this call, immediatly leaue their nets, and preach the Goſpell; but they left their nets and followed Chriſt Ieſus, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected another calling and deputation to that great worke: they were not as yet gifted for ſo high a calling. They muſt learne before they can teach. Firſt be Diſciples, before they can be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; Followers before Fiſhers.</p>
            <p>Many ouer-ſkip this degree, and make themſelues Apoſtles, that neuer knew what it was to be Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt Ieſus: Prophets they are made, that neuer knew the Schoole of the Prophets, nor what it is to be among the ſonnes of the Prophets: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing got a place in the Church; if you aske them, whence they came thither? if they will anſwer tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Iob 1.7.</note> they muſt ſay as Satan did, <hi>From compaſsing the earth, and from walking to and fro in it,</hi> as wanderers that could neuer ſettle in any good courſe of liuing; their indowments of body and mind are ſo meane, as that no Calling in the world could affoord them bread, for their paines, and therefore are faine to ſay (as it was Gods curie vpon <hi>Elies</hi> wicked ſons) <hi>Appoint me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam 2. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>I pray thee, to one of the Prieſts offices, that I may eate a morſell of bread.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou.
6.11.</note> Thus <hi>neceſsitie purſuing them like an armed man,</hi> as
<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, they flie from their enemie, and take hold on the hornes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15114:5"/> of the Altar; there they eate the Shew-bread, which is not lawfull to eate, but for the Prieſts onely.</p>
            <p>They that are driuen to this Calling for bread onely, and haue no other teſtimony of an inward calling, <hi>niſi quod inanitate inteſtina murmurant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plaui. Caſ.</note> for the moſt part they will tranſgreſſe for bread in the execution of their offices, <hi>&amp; fruſto panis conduci poſſunt, vel vri taceant, vel vti loquantur;</hi> they will ſpeake good of euill, or euill of good, as they ſhall finde to make beſt for their owne priuate aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>It is the Apoſtles ſentence, Act. 6. <hi>It is not meete to leaue the word of God, and ſerue tables:</hi> we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the ſentence, and ſay, It is not meet that men ſhould leaue ſeruing of tables, to become diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Gods word; It is not meete that Miniſters ſhould turne Seruing men; nor that Seruing-men and ſuch like, mercenary and mechanicall men voide of learning and gifts enabling, ſhould turne Miniſters. If euer God open the eyes of theſe men, to let them ſee the danger they are in, and feele the weight of the burden that is on their ſhoulders, and how vnable they are to beare it, they wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come in, fulfilling the prophecie of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> and ſay, <hi>I am no Prophet, but an husbandman:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>for man taught me to be an-herd-man from my youth.</hi> Though they haue now high places in the Church, and are great in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall purchaſes, though they ſit vpon pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the Temple, yet if they conſider that the Tempter ſet them there, to caſt them downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, to breake their necks, they will be glad to get
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15114:6"/> downe the faireſt way. Though they haue now the honour of Prophets, yet if they conſider that they are but the diuels workmen in Gods houſe, and that it may be ſaid of them as of <hi>Saul, Inuaſit eum ſpiritus malus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.10.</note>
               <hi>&amp; prophetabat;</hi> the euill ſpirit comes on them, and they prophecie: the euill ſpirit comes on them, and they turne Prieſts. When they well weigh theſe things, they will be glad for the peace of their conſciences to betake themſelues to their old trades againe, and leaue this Calling to thoſe that can better execute it, and that can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue their pedigrees from <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 7.64.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If you aske the cauſe, why in a well gouerned Church ſuch Locuſts can ſo ſwarme? One is, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Patrons giue their liuings vpon ſuch diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt termes, that no man of gifts or grace can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them; and therefore they are faine to find out ſuch as will accept of them vpon any termes, euen for <hi>Michaes</hi> wages,<note place="margin">Iudg.
17.10.</note> 
               <hi>ten ſhekels of ſiluer by the yeare, a ſuite of apparell, and meate and drinke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But others ſay, if no ſuch Miniſters were made, the Church ſhould not be peſtered with ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy creatures. It is true indeed; and if any that haue power to ordaine, admit ſuch wittingly and willingly, it will be heauie for him to anſwer for it before the great Biſhop of our ſoules. But to ſpeake truly in the iuſt defence of thoſe reuerend Fathers <hi>(quos vtinam omnes poſsem liberare)</hi> the cauſe for the moſt part is amongſt our ſelues: for it is not poſſible that any Biſhop ſhould know the life, and conuerſation, and education of euery one that is to be admitted into the miniſtery, but by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15114:6"/> of thoſe that know them. Miniſters and Gentlemen, for fauour or for by-reſpects, are too liberall of their hands, in giuing teſtimony to them whom either they know not, or know, not to be deſeruing; <hi>Et hinc illae lachrimae.</hi> They that thus commend vnworthy ones to the worke of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, let them conſider (though they be no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops) whether in ſo doing they haue not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Apoſtles precept,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>Ne cui cito manus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponas, Lay hands ſuddenly vpon no man, neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another ſort that out-run their calling too, which being called to follow, ſtraightwayes runne to this fiſhing before they be furniſhed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to be Diſciples, ſtraightwayes they run to the Apoſtolik function; contrary to the Apoſtles precept, <hi>Neophitus ne ſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let him not be a yong Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi> Before yeares and experience, reading and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helps bring them to maturitie of iudgement, they take vpon them to diuide the word of God to his people. Let it be granted that theſe be (ſome of them) of the Tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> (I meane yong men trained vp in the Schooles for the Miniſtery) yet for their forwardneſſe it may be ſaid of them truly, as the factious company to <hi>Moſes</hi> mutinouſly,<note place="margin">Numb.
16</note> 
               <hi>You take too much vpon you, yee ſonnes of Leui.</hi> Vnder the Law the Leuites had their appointed times for their ages,<note place="margin">Numb. 4.</note> before which they might haue no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to the ſeruice in the Tabernacle, though they were neuer ſo ripe and pregnant. It was not well with the ſacrifices when Prieſts boyes were permitted to intermeddle; they neuer came to do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15114:7"/> any good ſeruice either to God or to his Church:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.13.</note> but they came with their fleſh-hookes to fetch ſweet morſels from the Altar, and theſe cauſed the ſacrifices of the Lord to be deſpiſed. When the yong ſonnes of the Prophets ſhall be ſet to gather herbes to make pottage for the food of Gods houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, they may happely in ſtead of wholeſome pot-herbes, bring in
<hi>Colloquintida;</hi> that when the broth is ſerued in, they that taſte of it, may ſay, <hi>Mors in olla,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King 4.40.</note>
               <hi>O man of God, death is in the pot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not but God may enable ſome, as he did yong
<hi>Timothy</hi> with rare gifts for his worke, though they haue not many yeares: but it is not common, it is not ordinary. <hi>Et da mihi talem Timotheum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note>
               <hi>&amp; ego illum cibabo auro &amp; potabo balſamo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre the order and diſpoſition of the parts. Now followeth the parts of tne Text in order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Calling; <hi>Follow me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Qualifying; <hi>I will make you Fiſhers of men.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To follow Chriſt Ieſus, is not to follow him on foote onely,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus de bono virginali.</note> but to follow his precepts and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of life: <hi>Hunc in eo quiſque ſequitur, in quo imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> To follow Chriſt, is to be a Diſciple of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> to be a Diſciple, is to be a Chriſtian. For they that at the firſt were called Diſciples,<note place="margin">Act. 11.26.</note> afterwards at Antioch began to be called Chriſtians. Then to follow Chriſt, is to become good Chriſtians by the imitation of Chriſt. And this is the firſt ſtep to the office of the miniſtery: he muſt firſt be a good man that will be a good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And this firſt ſtep you (beloued, of the Laitie) muſt tread with vs. For though to follow Chriſt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15114:7"/> be here propounded as the firſt ſtaire to the office of preaching the word; yet elſe where our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles make it a common dutie belonging to all that beare the name of Chriſt, and are called Chriſtians. It is not ſaid of the Paſtors onely, but of the ſheepe alſo, that they follow the chiefe Shepheard: <hi>My ſheep heare my voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10.27.</note> 
               <hi>and they follow me.</hi> And to the whole Church at Epheſus, <hi>Be ye followers of God, as deare children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>and walke in loue, euen as Chriſt hath loued vs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſheep in Chriſts fold is barren of good works, <hi>They all go vp from the waſhing, euery one hath twins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant
4.2.</note> 
               <hi>and none is barren amongſt them. Shew me thy faith by thy works,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iames.</hi> Thy faith is beſt ſeen by thy following of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The life of a Chriſtian is his faith, the life of his faith, is his good workes: for <hi>faith without workes,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iames, is a dead faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.17.</note> A ſound Religion makes the profeſſors thereof <hi>trees of righteouſneſſe,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; not barren and dead trees, like the fig-tree our Sauiour Chriſt curſed, hauing leaues, and no fruite on it; but fruitfull trees,<note place="margin">Math. 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>Such as be planted in the houſe of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God; they ſhall bring forth fruit in their age, they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing.</hi> Though we do not teach you to merit heauen by your good workes, yet we muſt tell you, that your faith that is emptie of good works, is no good faith. Iuſtifying faith and a good conſcience are inſeparable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſay one to another as
<hi>Ruth</hi> ſaid to <hi>Naomi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 1 17.</note>
               <hi>Where thou dwelleſt, there will I dwell; and where thou dieſt, there will I die.</hi> A fruitleſſe faith is a dead faith.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15114:8"/> 
               <hi>Giue me children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.1.</note> ſaith <hi>Rachel</hi> to her huſband, <hi>or elſe I die.</hi> So ſaith Faith to the profeſſors thereof, Let good workes be the fruite of my wombe, or elſe I am but dead.</p>
            <p>We glorie much to compare our age enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to the darkneſſe of the age of our fore-fathers, what darkneſſe they ſat in, and what light we now do ſee. But if we looke well about vs, our wants are as great as theirs: they walked in darkneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had no light: but this is the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this our age, that light is come into the world, and men loue darkneſſe more then light, becauſe their deeds are euill. The former age in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was as <hi>Leah,</hi> bleare-eyd, yet fruitfull in many commendable workes: our age as <hi>Rachel,</hi> quicke ſighted, and beautifull to the eye, but barren: we are fruitfull indeed in profeſſed religion, but fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the true practiſe of pietie. Many that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to follow Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>aequis paſsibus,</hi> as it were at the very heeles, yet are found to halt, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit themſelues and their profeſſion,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.14.</note> and cauſe the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme. The more glorious you are in your profeſſion, if your actions be not anſwerable, the more do you wrong the Church wherein you ſtand, and wound your owne ſoules. Angels tongues, would haue Angels liues, Saints liues at the leaſt. But where there are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels tongues and diuels liues, there are diuels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate; Satan transformed into an Angel of light. It is better that wickedneſſe ſhould be ſeene in her owne colours, then vnder the hood and habit of vertue. A wicked Profeſſor is worſe then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15114:8"/> wicked man.</p>
            <p>But this dutie of following our maiſter Chriſt, is here chiefly intended to vs of the Miniſtery, wee muſt ſo follow, as that we muſt be examples to our flocks: we muſt follow Chriſt ſo neare, as that they may follow him in following vs; that we may ſay to them as the Apoſtle
<hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. 11.1. <hi>Be ye followers of me, as I am of Chriſt:</hi> ſo we muſt teach them as well by example of life in following, as by doctrine in preaching Chriſt.</p>
            <p>We are by reſemblance ſtarres;<note place="margin">Apoc.
1.10.</note> ſtarres we are in this life, and ſhall be ſtarres in heauen too, if we fulfill our Miniſtery effectually: Dan. 12.3. <hi>They that turne many to righteouſneſſe, ſhall ſhine as ſtarres in the firmament for euermore.</hi> Starred haue light, that points at our doctrine; ſtarres haue influence too,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.31.</note> that points at our good works. <hi>Canſt thou reſtraine the ſweet influence of the Pliades, or looſe the bands of Orion,</hi> ſaith almightie God to <hi>Iob.</hi> As the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers define, <hi>Stella eſt denſior pars ſui orbis,</hi> a ſtarre is a maſſier part of his orbe: ſo ſhould good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be more compact of goodnes and grace, then the reſt of the people, amongſt whom they liue.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, beloued brethren, ſtarres of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation, ſince our Calling is high and honorable, let the condition of our liues be ſuitable: let there not be diſparitie and diſproportion betwixt our callings and conuerſations: <hi>Ne ſit ſedes prima, &amp; vita ima.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Oceanum.</note> It is Saint <hi>Ieroms</hi> annotation vpon the name of Paſtor giuen to vs: <hi>Talis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligendus eſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, prae quo reliquus populus grex eſt.</hi> The like note may we as wel haue here from this name of Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15114:9"/> 
               <hi>Talis eſt eligendus Piſcator, prae quo reliquus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus piſces ſunt.</hi> He ought to be ſo conſpicuous for Gods graces eminent in him, that it may be ſaid of him as of the man whom God did chuſe to be the firſt King ouer his people Iſrael: <hi>Videte virum quem elegit Dominus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the man whom the Lord hath choſen, higher then all the people by the head, there is none like vnto him of all the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We aime at, not onely the groſſe and greateſt ſinnes of the people, but euen at the leaſt too, euen motes muſt we take away: and how cleane muſt he be himſelfe, that ſhould be a mote-finder in other mens liues? We may not go with beames in our owne eyes, to pull out motes out of our brothers eyes: if we do, they will as ſoone ſuffer vs to pull their eyes out of their heads, as any motes out of their eyes. For ſuch is the peruerſneſſe of people, (I may well call it peruerſneſſe in them) they will not be taught by their doctrines whoſe liues teach not too;<note place="margin">Math. 7 5.</note> but they haue learned to ſay, <hi>Hypocrite, firſt pull the beame out of thine owne eye, then ſhalt thou ſee more clearely to pull the mote out of thy brothers eye.</hi> Motes in our eyes are beames, they are beames in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the peoples account, nay, they are beames in Gods account; I would to God then they might be ſo in our account too. Our motes are beames in Gods account: for marke it, and it is obſerued by
<hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dial. lib. <hi>6,</hi> cap.
<hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that vnder the Law there was as much ſacrifice to be offered for the ſinne of the Prieſt, as for the whole multitude; to ſignifie, that for the dignity of his place, and for the common miſchiefe enſuing vpon his fall by example, his ſin weighed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15114:9"/> as much as the ſinne of all the people. And the Prieſts daughter that did not intermeddle in the Prieſts office, yet in regard of her deſcent and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſhe comes of, her ſinne was much more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous then the ſame ſinne in another woman:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.
21.9.</hi> Cum reliquis vero in eadem culpa depre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit mitius ageba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Exod.
<hi>22.16</hi>
               </note> if ſhe played the whore, ſhe muſt be burned with fire, though the ſame ſinne in another had an eaſier pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>The world is much giuen to fault-finding with vs for our liues, and many times without a cauſe: for they thinke to extenuate their owne faults, by ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauating ours;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.12.</note> and pleade in defence of their ſins like <hi>Adam: The woman that thou gaueſt me, gaue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and I did eate.</hi> The Paſtor that thou didſt ſet ouer me, was an example vnto me of ſinning, and I did ſinne. <hi>Querentes licentiam male viuendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de vita &amp; moribus clir. Serm. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>querunt ſibi exempla malè viuentium, &amp; multos infamant, vt ſocios inueniſſe videantur:</hi> And if they find ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples amongſt vs, though it excuſe not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, yet it makes vs inexcuſable if we be guiltie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Voi ſoli non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis perire. Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Beloued, it ſtands vs in hand to looke to our own footing. We liue not to our ſelues; many do ſtand or fall by our example. The ſinnes of <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes made the people of the Lord to treſpaſſe. And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary ſinnes muſt haue exemplarie puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The next in the Text, is qualifying: <hi>I will make you Fiſhers of men.</hi> Firſt, Fiſhers muſt be ſkilfull <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> both to guide their boate vpon the tempeſtuous ſea, and alſo to know when, and how, and where to caſt out their nets to make a draught.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Fiſhers muſt be painfull, alwayes bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15114:10"/> about their fiſhing, either letting downe their nets for a draught, or pulling them vp, or launch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the deepe, or haling to the ſhore, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or waſhing their nets.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Fiſhers muſt agree in their worke, elſe by diſcord and wrangling amongſt themſelues the worke is hindered that it neuer goeth forward. When <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>I go a fiſhing;</hi> the reſt agree, and ſay, <hi>We will go with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Fiſhers, if they be compared to the fiſhes that they lay for, one man (though but a fiſherman) is of more worth then millions of fiſhes. Fiſhers then, fiſhers in this kind, fiſhers of men are of no baſe trade. The ſubiect commends the work: they fiſh not for fiſhes, but for men: for men, not to prey vpon them, but to ſaue them; not for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or goods of men, but for the ſoules of men; they fiſh for the ſoules of men, purchaſed by the blood of the Sonne of God. Thus by the name of Fiſher-man, we haue commended vnto vs theſe foure qualities in Gods fiſher-men, Skilfulneſſe, Painfulneſſe, Concord, and Dignitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1</note>Firſt for Skilfulneſſe. Since our fiſhing is not for tranſitory things, but for gaining of ſoules to God, it behoueth vs to vſe our beſt ſkill for the effecting of ſo great a worke: all the helpes of nature and art are to be ſought for for this work: arts and tongues, meditations and readings, ſhould be hand-maides for this Art.</p>
            <p>Gods fiſher-men here by the like metaphors are called <hi>Gods builders,</hi> 1. Cor. 3. In the building of the materiall Temple, there muſt not be a ſtone layed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15114:10"/> nor ſcarce a pin driuen but by diuine art taught of God. How ſhall men vntaught then preſume to worke in Gods ſpirituall building with vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red morter, and hands vnſanctified for the worke?</p>
            <p>It is intollerable and impious boldneſſe, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnſkilfull know-little ſhall preſume at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to diuide the ſacred word of God, the holy Goſpell to Gods people, and that in the ſight and preſence of God himſelfe, and all his holy Angels. He that doth this worke aright,<note place="margin">Iſa. 12.3.</note> doth <hi>draw water from the well of ſaluation</hi> for the people of God, ſaith the Prophet. Let therefore euery faithfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor draw this water; but euery one with his owne pitcher. If any haue not a pitcher, or but a broken pitcher, how ſhould he draw. I may ſay with the woman of Samaria, <hi>the well is deepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.11.</note> and if thou haſt nothing to draw with, whence ſhouldſt thou haue that water of life.</p>
            <p>Many to auoide the imputation of dumbe dogs in the Church, breake ſilence, and become Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſometimes (through ignorance) of vnſound doctrine, many times of vnſauory, that worketh nothing either to the information of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to the reformation of the affections of the hearer. I ſpeake not to diſcourage any of meane gifts, if they can be any wayes profitab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. He that hath but one talent, if he vſe it well, ſhall haue his reward with God. But I would haue no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that he hath a talent in his napkin, when he hath but an emptie napkin.</p>
            <p>This frothy kind of preaching makes the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to contemne ſo high and holy an ordinance:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15114:11"/> when after a long and tedious Sermon heard with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruit, it may be ſaid of the hungry multitude, as the Prophet ſpeakes of Ephraim, Hoſ. 12.1. <hi>Ephraim is fed with the wind:</hi> for they get nothing but emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe: <hi>Vox eſt, praeterea nihil,</hi> a great ſound of much food, but no ſound food at all.</p>
            <p>Of ſuch teachers, which through ignorance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times proue teachers of lies, I ſay no more, but as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid to his comfortleſſe comforters, Iob 13.5. <hi>O that you would hold your tongues, that it might be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto you for wiſedome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of theſe, though but meanly qualified, yet if in humilitie they would take notice of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their gifts, they might be more profitable in more ſilence: but whileſt they thinke to cleare themſelues of inſufficiencie and of idleneſſe by their often preaching, they are faine for want of matter, to fill vp their houres with vaine tautalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and idle diſcourſes, that the meaneſt of their auditory can diſcerne their barrenneſſe, and count their preaching but babbling.</p>
            <p>When the people of Rome heard that the fields belonging to ſome of their Colonies waxed bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, their aduice was (as <hi>Plinie</hi> recordeth) that the Huſband-men ſhould <hi>melius arare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nat. hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; minus ſerere,</hi> plough better, and ſow leſſe: ſo when Gods field waxeth barren, and the people profit not by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, by reaſon of a negligent kind of preaching, I hope it wil not be counted vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counſell to ſuch as cannot ſpeake often, and well too, that they ſpend more time in their ſtudies, and be leſſe ſeene in their pulpits. If they haue fiſhed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15114:11"/> all night and caught nothing, it were not amiſſe that they ſhould ſit downe a while vpon the ſhore and mend their nets, afterwards with Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing they may fiſh with better ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Till I come</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy) giue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to reading, to exhortation, and to doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.13.</note> The better we giue attendance to reading, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we ſhall be furniſhed for doctrine and for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. <hi>He that heareth, ſpeaketh continually,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> Prou.
21.28. And ſince <hi>auditus eſt ſenſus diſciplinae;</hi> by hearing (in this place I take it) is not onely meant the hearing of the eare, but any means whereby the minde is enriched with knowledge, whether it be hearing, or reading, or meditation, or conference: in this ſenſe then, <hi>he that heareth ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth continually.</hi> But he that will be ſpeaking conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and neuer heareth, ſhall be ſure alwayes to ſpeake that that is not worth the hearing. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the people ſhould heare fewer Sermons to their edification, then many without profit.<note place="margin">Col.
4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let our words be gracious alwayes,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,
<hi>and ſeaſoned with ſalt:</hi> and let vs not more regard the number of them, then the weight.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>I had rather</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) ſpeake fiue words with vnderſtanding, and to the edification of others, then ten thouſand in a barbarous tongue without profit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to thoſe that are able to be frequent, the counſell of the King and Preacher is to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Eccleſ. 11.6. <hi>In the morning ſow thy ſeed, and in the euening let not thy hand ceaſe: for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper, this or that, or whether both alike.</hi> But to others (ſuch as now I ſpeake of) they ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15114:12"/> ſpeake no oftener in the name of God to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then when almightie God commands them to ſpeake: and then onely God commands to ſpeake, when he furniſheth his ſpeaker with good matter; according to that of <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob,</hi> Iob 32.18. <hi>I am full of matter, and the Spirit within me compelleth me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It behoueth vs, not onely to haue the tongues of the learned, to ſpeake ſound &amp; iuſtifiable doctrine; but alſo to haue the tongues of the diſcreet too, to ſpeake ſeaſonably, reſpecting perſons, times and places: this was the Prophet <hi>Iſaies</hi> gift, Iſa. 50.4.
<hi>The Lord hath giuen me the tongue of the learned, that I ſhould know to miniſter a word in due ſeaſon to him that is weary.</hi> It behoueth vs to know how to giue to euery one his portion in due ſeaſon; milke to them that are weake, ſtrong meate to the ſtronger. We muſt learne to know the maladies of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and how to cure them, and not always (which the Prophet reproues) to heale the ſores of Gods people with ſweet words.<note place="margin">Ier. 6.14.</note> If the wound be feſtring and putrifie, we muſt know how to make inciſion; if it be a broken wound, how to heale it vp. We muſt know how to vſe ſometimes oyle to ſupple a wound, ſometimes wine to ſearch it: the good Samaritan vſed both, Luk. 10. he powred in wine and oyle.</p>
            <p>A ſkilfull Paſtor muſt ſometimes be a <hi>Boanerges,</hi> that is, the ſonne of thunder, to thunder out the curſes of the Law againſt obſtinate ſinners. Again, he muſt ſometimes be a
<hi>Barnabas,</hi> that is, the ſonne of conſolation, to comfort with the ſweet promiſes of the Goſpell thoſe that feele the weight and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15114:12"/> of their ſinnes. It is not the leaſt part of our ſkill to know how to reprehend with good effect. Many do loſe many times the reprehenſion and the man too, becauſe they are not cautelous in the application of it: if it haue the leaſt ſauour of ill wil and reuenge, it marres all. The very matter of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion hath in it a certaine kind of harſhneſſe and bitterneſſe; therefore muſt be qualified in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. We muſt do as Phyſitions, that vſe to giue their wholeſome-bitter pils lapt vp in ſweete-meates.</p>
            <p>To a naturall man to be reprehended for his ſin, his ſweet ſin, his darling ſin, oh it goes like dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to his heart; he is ready to crie out, Murder, murder;<note place="margin">Act. 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>Wilt thou kill me as thou didſt the Egyptian yeſterday?</hi> There is in this a Chriſtian art to be vſed, <hi>Vt ſecantem gladium ſentiat aeger antequam cernit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> that the ſoule-ficke man may gulpe downe his phyſicke before he is aware, and let it worke on him afterwards.</p>
            <p>Many omit this dutie of reprehending altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpecially towards great ones, leſt they ſhould offend; and ſo do not fulfill their miniſtery wholy, but in part onely: that is no good courſe:<note place="margin">Habet etenium ſuum virus blan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a adulatio. Seneca.</note> great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt not be alwayes poiſoned with flattery; Is there for them <hi>no balme in Gilead?</hi> Muſt they be alwayes ſerued in with <hi>butter in a lordly diſh</hi> to their owne confuſion? No, they muſt be admoniſhed too, but in good termes, and with due reſpect.<note place="margin">De regim. Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. ad Euſtoch.</note> 
               <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil eſt in rectore periculoſius quam vana humilitas ad correptionem erga ſuperbos protervoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſubditos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierom,</hi> It is dangerous humilitie to be afraid to ſpeake in Gods cauſe, and for the gaining of any,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15114:13"/> of what degree ſoeuer. Fiſhers do not vſe to caſt nets for ſmal fiſhes, &amp; let great ones go: we may not ſo make fiſh of one, and fleſh of another: yet regard muſt be had to the qualitie of the perſon. <hi>Is it fit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> to
<hi>Iob) to ſay vnto a King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 34.18.</note>
               <hi>thou art wicked; and to Princes, Ye are vngodly?</hi> No; Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> would haue a difference obſerued towards perſons of meaner qualitie: <hi>Seniorem ne increpaueris, ſed obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora vt patrem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreate him as a father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> could well brooke that <hi>Nathan</hi> ſhould tell him of his greateſt ſinnes; becauſe as he did his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage faithfully from the Lord, ſo he did it with due reuerence, and reſpect to the perſon of the King. <hi>Vir ſanctus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard) &amp; regem conſiderans, &amp; peccatorem.</hi> But whem <hi>Shimei</hi> rebuked him for the ſame ſinne, he was highly diſpleaſed with him, and that iuſtly; for he vſed vnreuerent and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull railing on the King.</p>
            <p>The ſecond qualitie in Fiſher-men, is Painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Fiſhing is a painfull trade. As <hi>Peters</hi> trade of fiſhing for fiſhes of the Sea was painfull, in the ſweate of his browes: ſo this his trade in fiſhing for men is as painfull, in the ſweate of his braine. For as in that he had many times ſore trauell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fruite: ſo in this it may ſometimes befall him to haue cauſe to complaine with the Prophet
<hi>Iſay, I haue laboured in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 49.4. and
55.2.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſpent my ſtrength in vaine: all the day long haue I ſtretched out my hands to a rebellious people.</hi> This Chaire of
<hi>Peters,</hi> is not a Chaire to ſit and ſleepe in: he that ſits in it, muſt think that ſpoken to him, which our maiſter Chriſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15114:13"/> ſpake to Peter: <hi>Peter, loueſt thou me?</hi> then <hi>feed my ſheepe, feed my lambes; if thou loueſt me Peter, feede. The lips of the righteous</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) feede many.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10 21.</note> And the hungrie flock of Chriſts fold expect their food from them that are their Paſtors: they muſt therefore with all diligence giue them their meate in due ſeaſon. Many Paſtors are not painfull in feeding, becauſe their flocks are ignorant, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not iudge of their paines: and ſome Paſtors reioyce that they haue ſuch a people, with whom they may be idle, and none complaine of their idleneſſe, whether it be ſilent idleneſſe in not preaching, or ſpeaking idleneſſe in preaching without medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Such a ſtupiditie in the people, ſhould be no reioycing to the Paſtor, but rather ſtirre him vp to greater paines.<note place="margin">Crat.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iguri habitae.</note>
               <hi>Impoſtoris eſt non probi viri ſtupidos &amp; ignaros quaerere auditores quos poſsit fallere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi> Some there are that preſuming vpon their owne extemporall facultie, and their peoples ſimplicitie, bid faire for that curſe that almightie God denounceth againſt thoſe that do the worke of the Lord negligently, Ier. 48.10. In the
34 of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel,</hi> amongſt many other curſes which almightie God threatneth againſt idle Paſtors, this is one, that they ſhall be depriued of their gifts. A talent hid in a napkin, ſhall be taken away. Excellent gifts are loſt many times, becauſe they are not vſed. Wherefore let the heart indite a good matter, and then the tongue will be the pen of a ready writer: but if the heart wax fat with idleneſſe, no maruell then though the tongue cleaue to the roofe of the mouth, and the right hand forget her cunning.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15114:14"/>And this is not the onely puniſhment of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be depriued of goodneſſe. A field, if it lie vntilled, is not onely barren of good fruits, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fertile of weeds: ſo is it with our mindes, if they be not buſied with good, they ſet themſelues on worke to miſchiefe: for God hath giuen to man a working mind,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.11.</note> that cannot reſt. The world is in mans heart, ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> The mind in this may be compared to a Mill, which if the wind carry about emptie, it ſetteth it ſelfe on fire: when mans wit ceaſeth to work good and profitable things, it ſets it ſelfe on fire to miſchiefe; and then the more wit and learning the man hath, the more pernicious an enginer he proues of wicked attempts. <hi>Magna etenim ingenia nil efferunt mediocre.</hi> And hence comes Sects and Schiſmes in the Church, whileſt that ſome for their ſtomack againſt their ſuperiors, and other miſdemeanours, might not without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Church be permitted to go on in their factious preaching, but muſt rather be enioyned ſilence, haue now leiſure enough to vſe their tongues and their pens for railing and raiſing vp tumults againſt the Church. As ſoone as euer they left feeding, ſtraight wayes they began to deſtroy: as ſoone as they left building, they began to pull downe, euen that themſelues had built.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the ſecond qualitie of Gods Fiſher-men, Painfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The third is Concord and agreement, which is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> moſt needfull: for without it, no good can be done. For as the fiſhers in the Sea being to lay their nets, if they ſtirre and trouble the waters, they fruſtrate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15114:14"/> their worke, that they can catch no fiſhes: ſo Gods fiſher-men, if there be diſturbance and contentions amongſt them, they thereby ſo alienate the minds of men, that they can win none. Therefore our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt here makes choice of ſuch as the bond of nature firmly bindes to concord and amitie, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinsfolks,
<hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> his brother, <hi>Iames</hi> and
<hi>Iohn</hi> his brother. And let the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> tell them <hi>how good and how comely a thing it is, brethren to dwell together in vnitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Barke is a fiſher-boate, not a man of warre; it is not furniſhed with mortall engines and warlike munition, but with nets onely to take fiſh withall. If there be amongſt the Apoſtles a ſword or two, they muſt take heed how they vnſheath them. If
<hi>Peter</hi> deſerued to be reprehended for drawing vpon <hi>Malchus,</hi> what reprehenſion thinke you had he bin worthy of, had he drawne vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his felowes?</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> diſtinguiſheth the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie in the ſhip in this order: there is the father, the brethren, and the hired ſeruants; and theſe are all names and relatiues of loue; the father muſt needs loue his children, the children muſt loue and honour their father, and loue one another, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants that labour together, muſt loue one another, and loue, honour and obey their maiſter and their maiſters children. The father ſits at the ſterne to rule and direct the ſhip; for age hath made him leſſe able to take corporall paines, but experience hath made him fitter for gouernment.</p>
            <p>The reuerend Fathers of the Church guide the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15114:15"/> ſterne of Gods ſhip, they are ſet ouer Gods Church <hi>Praeſunt vt proſint.</hi> If the Church be a ſhip floting vpon the ſeas, they are the pilots; if ſhe be a flocke wandring vpon the mountaines, they are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, they rule the ſheep of Gods paſture, they rule <hi>non tanquam ſuas, ſed tanquam Chriſti oues,</hi> not as Lords of Gods heritage, but as Stewards, and ſuch as muſt giue an account for them. If there be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betweene Paſtor and Paſtor, or betweene flock and flocke, theſe interpoſe themſelues in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, and with their grauitie and wiſedome take vp the matter, ſometimes but with a fatherly admonition, like <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot, Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee, between thee and me, neither between thy herd-men and my herd-men, for we be brethren:</hi> ſometimes with a more ſtrict hand and compulſory ſentence (as the cauſe ſhall require) <hi>veniunt cum virga,</hi> with the ſtaffe of diſcipline. They wil always know to put a difference betwixt the iarres of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (which may ſometimes fall out in the beſt gouerned families) and the warres that are raiſed by enemies, and in their cenſures they will diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh theſe, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> when the ſtrife was betwixt two brethren, two Iſraelites in Egypt; he takes vp the matter with a friendly checke, <hi>Sirs</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye are brethren, why then do you wrong one to another?</hi> But when the ſtrife was betwixt a brother and an enemy, an Iſraelite and an Egyptian, he kils the Egyptian, and defends the Iſraelite.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt well knew that concord and amitie is beſt maintained amongſt the feweſt in number; therfore when he ſends forth his Diſciples
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15114:15"/> to preach the Goſpell to the world, he ioynes two and two in a commiſſion together. When two and two are ioyned together, and beare the yoke equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwixt them, then the worke goeth well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: but if they be ioyned at the tailes, that one drawes one way, and another another way, like <hi>Samſons</hi> foxes, two and two to a fire-brand,<note place="margin">Iudg. 15 4.</note> then their waiwardneſſe tends to nothing elſe but to combuſtion.</p>
            <p>Beloued brethren,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.19.</note> the beſt fruite of our lips is peace; let vs pray for the peace of Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.</note> Peace be within her walls, and plenteouſneſſe within her pallaces. If we ſhall ſet vp altar againſt altar, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine againſt doctrine, diſcipline againſt diſcipline, ceremonie againſt ceremonie, or rather (as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſome is) no ceremonie againſt lawfull and profitable ceremonies, what do we elſe but breake downe the walls of Ieruſalem? we cauſe our friends to be ſad, and our enemies to reioyce. It was the argument of <hi>Dion</hi> to his contentious ſouldiers,<note place="margin">In vita eius
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ud
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atarch.</note> pointing to the Caſtle of their enemies, <hi>Sirs</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your enemies ſee your mutinous behauiour.</hi> All the enemies that the Church hath, do ſee, and are glad to ſee, and make vſe of what they ſee, when they behold our contentions.</p>
            <p>Some there are, that for the maintenance of an opinion about the wearing of a garment, or an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ceremonie, are ſo violent and virulent, that they will not care to breake peace with fathers and brethren, when others of better moderation can tell them with Saint
<hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de ſerm. De
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mont. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>28,</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Non ideo debent oues odiſſe veſtimentum ſuum, quia illo ſe occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15114:16"/> lupi,</hi> ſheepes cloathing are neuer the worſe for ſheepes wearing, though wolues weare the like.</p>
            <p>In theſe differences and ſuch like, ſome vſe ſuch bitterneſſe and vehemencie, that they dare call for fire from heauen to conſume their brethren that are contrary minded, <hi>Tantaene animis coeleſtibus irae,</hi> ſhould heauenly minds be ſo reuengefull? Do they well know of what ſpirit they are of? is this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly zeale? is this fire kindled at Gods altar? is this wiſedome from aboue? no, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> tels vs, that <hi>the wiſedome that is from aboue, is firſt pure, then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, gentle, eaſie to be intreated,</hi> Iam. 3.17. Where there are ſuch ſeditions, there is no other wiſdome, but earthly, ſenſuall and diuelliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> I come now to the fourth and laſt part of ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie betwixt theſe fiſhers of men, and fiſhers of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, which points at their dignitie. In this fiſhing, the nets are the ſacred Scriptures; the fiſhes, men; the ſhip, the Church; the catching of fiſhes, the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſoules to God. Where the fiſhes beare the image of the eternall God, and are redeemed by the blood of the Sonne of God, how great honour is it to be a Fiſher-man in ſuch a ſea? God giues honour to our calling; and where it is deſerued <hi>double honour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17. Heb. 2.2. Exod. 20.19.</note> Once our worke was the worke of Angels; afterwards (for mans frailtie) the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall office was committed to men, but thoſe men to be ſtiled with the title of
<hi>Angels.</hi> Though we be but earthen veſſels, yet we beare the heauenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and the veſſell ought to be eſteemed for the treaſure it containeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15114:16"/>The Church is <hi>the Kings Daughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.14.</note> 
               <hi>all glorious within:</hi> why then ſhould a Kings ſonne thinke her too meane a match for himſelfe to be maried vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to?</p>
            <p>The King of glorie Chriſt Ieſus, whileſt he liued vpon earth, thought not this calling too meane for him, but liued in it, and died in it.</p>
            <p>Wel, the Calling is a good Calling, good enough for any man, and too good for any man that thinks it not good enough. But now though there is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour enough for vs with God and with good men, yet the profane world hath nothing but ſcorne and contempt for vs; and we may complaine with the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.4.</note> 
               <hi>Our ſoule is filled with the ſcornfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch of the wealthy, and with the deſpitefulneſſe of the proud.</hi> It was not ſo from the beginning;<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.14.</note> it was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe when good king <hi>Dauid</hi> reioyced to dance before the Arke in a linnen Ephod. And once that name and office of Prieſt, which now is contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, it was a Kings ambition to affect it.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 26.16.</note> When
<hi>Vz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zia,</hi> though he were a King, thought it an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his honour, that he might be a Prieſt too. But now <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſinne is very rife. <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ſin, you will ſay, what is that?<note place="margin">1. King. 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>Ieroboam made the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the people Prieſts.</hi> That is their ſinne, that make baſe and vnworthy Prieſts, or any wayes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and procure their making. Yea but
<hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> ſinne is of a larger extent: <hi>Ieroboam made the meaneſt of the people Prieſts.</hi> It is the ſinne of this age to make their Prieſts meaner then the meaneſt of what tribe ſoeuer he be: if he be a Prieſt once, that is an attainter of his blood, (in the eſtimation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15114:17"/> of ſome;) and if he be nobly deſcended, an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of his Gentery; ſo is this high Calling diſhonoured and diſeſteemed. God grant this ſinne be not layed to the charge of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15114:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
